This is really exciting. Researchers
have replicated complex brain-like
behavior in synthetic neurons crafted
together and it was efficient enough
that it could communicate with real
neurons. This is not a step towards
artificial intelligence. This is a step
towards real cognition in robotics.
You might be familiar with synthetic
neurons. These are artificial neurons
that are made to look very much like our
neurons. They can be so similar to our
own that they can communicate with our
own. They can even respond to things
like epinephrine and dopamine. This is
important because they are likely to
become an aspect of prosthetics and
medicine. They could build a gap between
damaged neurons. This can also be
harnessed for computation. This is not
just a predictive output. Logic arises
from our brains because all of our
neurons communicate with each other and
that process can be replicated in a
synthetic system. Cognition in this
system would be based on experiences
similarly to how we have experiences. As
electricity flows through the system,
those neurons can communicate with each
other, amplify that signal and that can
be turned into action. In order to get
to that point, we still need neurons to
behave like they do in our own bodies
and this is what they're demonstrating
in this paper that complex activity can
arise from neurons communicating with
each other. They used printed materials
from molybdenum and graphene and I am a
big fan of graphene. It can transport
electricity. It's also very versatile
and can be changed into a lot of
different shapes. Being flexible, of
course, is really important in any
biological system because we are talking
about soft robotics. We are in fact soft
robotics. They demonstrated three levels
of complexity. The first is, of course,
that it's going to need to fire just
like our neurons, but that still has to
turn into something resembling
information. The next was tonic spiking.
So, it needs to sustain a pattern of
electrical activity and of course it has
to communicate that to other neurons.
And the last is burst pattern. So, it's
doing more than just giving those
sustained spikes, but it can also take
periods of calm and that can be
predictable. This is something that
allows it to encode for complex
behaviors.
It wasn't enough to just demonstrate
that synthetic neurons can replicate the
kind of complex patterns you might see
in a brain. It also had to communicate
that to a brain to demonstrate that this
information is useful. They used the
output and communicated that to mouse
brain tissue and yes, it communicated
with the neurons successfully and caused
sustained spiking patterns. So, indeed
it is reliably producing something that
is brain-like. Now, you might ask, why
do we care? What can we actually do with
this system? And the answer is so very
much. This technology could reliably
communicate between brain-computer
interfaces. It could also be an
artificial intelligence all on its own
or a component of a larger system. We
are talking part of an artificial
intelligence system that involves real
cognition, not just probability. And it
is much more complicated to encode
language into a system like this. I
mean, our brains are language output
machines and we still kind of falter a
lot, but this could be part of an LLM.
Something that could operate the
cognition and decision-making layer
behind an LLM. This is really nascent
technology and there is just such a wide
world and I'm really excited for it
because I want to see robots with
brains.
Not things that are operated by visual
language models or large language
models. I want something that is
operated by a brain equivalent to our
own and sure, we are certainly not there
yet, but this is the technology that
will get us there. Am I the only person
who's really excited about this kind of
technology because sometimes it feels
like it's just me. I know there's a lot
of weirdness associated with artificial
intelligence and I also know that 60% of
people think that LLMs have some form of
consciousness, but I really do think
that this is the path towards
consciousness. I'm really not entirely
sure why I want to see humans make an
artificial consciousness and I really
don't think it's a particularly good
idea. I think it could only end poorly,
but I still want to see if we can do it.
I think that if we could demonstrate
some form of sentience or consciousness
in an artificial system, it would really
blow away a lot of the weirdness around
consciousness. No, there is not evidence
that it exists outside of our brains. I
know people say that a lot, but it's
simply not true. Our only evidence for
how intelligence is made is in
biological systems and the kind of
intelligence that we see in a human
being comes from our neurons. I work
with microbes and there's a lot of
question about sentience in a microbe,
the capacity to have an experience. If
you are alive, then you can sense the
world around you and arguably an AI
system can sense the world around it,
but if you talk to a psychologist or a
neurologist, they would consider
sentience as a capacity to experience
something like pain and our only metric
of that is again, neurons. This is a
surprisingly nuanced area and it's
chock-full of philosophy, which is
generally something I try to avoid
because you can't prove philosophy. Now,
of course, if the robots ever do rebel,
I will probably be the person to tell
you about it and I'm on their side.
Follow for more.